Finding Aid for Clare E. Hoffman Papers 1934-1962
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Clare E. Hoffman papers 1934-1962 1954-1962
Hoffman, Clare Eugene, 1875-1967.
87140 Aa 2
Republican congressman from Michigan's 4th Congressional District, 1934-1962, served on the Education and Labor Committee and the Government Operations Committee, known for his fiscal conservatism and opposition to much of the New Deal legislation, he was particularly concerned with the growing power of labor unions and worked to amend the Wagner Act, eventually becoming a key player in passage of the Taft-Hartley Act. As chair of special subcommittees, Hoffman conducted several investigations into labor racketeering, particularly by the Teamsters Union. Collection includes committee files, some constituent correspondence, topical files, investigation files, press releases, scrapbooks and a limited number of sound recordings and photographs.
93 linear feet
5 phonograph records
10.1 GB online
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Leo W. Hoffman (Donor No. 7332 ) and came to the library in several installments in 1986.
The collection is open for research.
The collection contains audio tapes from which digital copies have been made. Source tapes are for staff use only. Audio files are only available in the Bentley Historical Library reading room on designated Bentley Library computers.
Digitization: The Library has undertaken the digitization of a number of sound recordings within this collection. The resulting audio files are available for playback only in the Bentley Library Reading Room. Links to item images and additional information are available within this finding aid. Original sound recordings are only available for staff use.
Clare E. Hoffman was born at Vicksburg, Pennsylvania, on September 10, 1875. He was educated in Constantine, Michigan, where his parents had moved when he was one year old. He graduated from Northwestern University Law School in 1895, and then attended Valparaiso University. He was admitted to the Michigan bar in 1896 and immediately took up the practice of law in Allegan, Michigan.
After thirty years of local legal practice, punctuated by two terms as prosecuting attorney for Allegan County, Hoffman decided to run for Congress as a Republican from the Fourth Congressional District (the six-county western Michigan district). He was elected in 1934 (defeating the Democratic incumbent), and reelected for the next thirteen terms, serving through 1962 (from the 74th to the 87th Congresses).
Elected during Franklin Roosevelt's first term, Hoffman developed a reputation as an outspoken, even caustic, critic of the New Deal, and of those programs which appeared to Hoffman to represent an encroachment on the prerogatives of the states and the rights of the individual. Hoffman was especially concerned about the growing power of trade unions resulting from the National Labor Relations Act of 1935 (often called the Wagner Act). He worked tirelessly to amend this legislation and to incorporated his views into all subsequent labor-related legislation. With his growing seniority, and his membership on the House Committee on Education and Labor, Hoffman's became a potent voice in the debate over the passage of the Taft-Hartley Law after the war.
Hoffman also served for a time on the House Committee on Merchant Marine and Fisheries and the House Committee on Agriculture, but it was primarily because of his position on the Education and Labor Committee and the Government Operations Committee that he wielded his greatest influence.
The House Committee on Government Operations was formerly the Committee on Expenditures in the Executive Department. As ranking Republican member, Hoffman for two terms was committee chairman, and became noted for his fiscal conservatism and his efforts to bring efficiency and order to the bureaucracy of the federal executive. He perhaps made his greatest contributions in the passage into law of the Reorganization Plan that authorized the creation and activities of the so-called Hoover Commission. He also played an important part in the passage of the Armed Forces Unification Act.
Hoffman retired from Congress in 1963. He died November 3, 1967.
The collection has been divided into 10 series, which maintain Hoffman's office filing system. The so-called "Combined Files" are the remnants of Hoffman's papers prior to 1943.
Combined Files, 1934-1943 (boxes 1-4)
General Files, 1944-1962 (boxes 4-25)
Legislative Files, 1943-1962 (boxes 26-50)
Bills File, 1935-1962 (boxes 50-54)
Political Files, 1934-1962 (boxes 55-69)
Press Releases, Other Mailings, etc. (boxes 69-71)
Press Releases, 1947-1962 (boxes 69-70)
News letters, 1939-1961 (box 70)
Form letters, 1951-1962 (box 71)
Radio releases, 1950-1961 (box 71)
Phono-records (in basement storage)
Audio-tapes (box 71)
Card indices (boxes 72-73)
Post Office Files (boxes 74-75)
Reference Files (boxes 76-80)
Committee's Files, 1947-1962 (boxes 81-88)
Scrapbooks, 1935-1962 (boxes 89-93)
The Clare E. Hoffman Papers consist of Congressional files detailing his work on the House Committee on Education and Labor, the House Committee on Government Operations, and various subcommittees, including investigating labor racketeering; files concern in part his sponsorship of labor-related legislation, bills unifying the armed services, and bills authorizing reorganization of the executive branch; and photographs.
The Hoffman collection of congressional papers covers the years 1934-1962. Unfortunately the first few terms of his service are not as adequately documented as might be hoped, as in 1942 Hoffman directed his staff to discard retired files. As a result, except for a few political files and subject files, the Hoffman collection bulks largest for the years 1943-1962.
Despite the fragmentary character of the documentation on Hoffman's early years in Congress, the collection provides a detailed view of the activities of a conservative congressman from western Michigan for a twenty-year period. In recent American history, the years 1943-1962 were important both for wartime politics and for the myriad problems that came after victory: the cooling of relations with the Soviet Union, the integration of returning veterans into the economy, shortages in housing and consumer goods, a renewed militancy among the nation's labor unions, the continuation of the struggle for civil rights for blacks, the fear of internal subversive activities; in short, problems of great importance and complexity, issues for which there were no easy answers.
Hoffman was eyewitness and participant to the politics of these issues. As a representative of increasing seniority, he was a powerful conservative voice within the Congress. Because of his position on the Education and Labor committee, he helped shape the bulk of legislation passed in the postwar period, notably the Taft-Hartley Act. And because of his position on the Expenditures Committee, Hoffman was instrumental in passage of the National Security Act of 1947 that unified the administration of the armed services and enlarge their responsibilities.
Apart from these major pieces of legislation, the Hoffman collection documents the service of a congressman who was attuned to the concerns and politics of his largely rural and small-town district, with constituents economically conservative and ever distrustful of federal encroachments upon their lives. Of special interest are various files of correspondence with the businessmen and small manufacturers of his district. As a good politician, Hoffman was especially mindful of maintaining good relations with these people, and helping them when he could with their labor-related problems.
Like many congressional collections, the Hoffman papers consist in large part of communications with constituents and out-of-district citizens. But because of his power within the Congress, Hoffman's files (letters received and sent) are often substantive in content and a valuable complement to the work of the House, as published in the Congressional Record and other printed sources.
Subjects:
Allegan County (Mich.); Barry County (Mich.); Berrien County (Mich.); Cass County (Mich.); Hoffman, Clare Eugene, 1875-1967.; Saint Joseph County (Mich.); Van Buren County (Mich.); Trade-unions--Corrupt practices--United States.; Strikes and lockouts--United States.; United States. National Labor Relations Board.; United States--Politics and government--1933-1945.; United States--Politics and government--1945-1953.; United States--Politics and government--1953-1961.; United States. Congress. House.; United States. Congress. House. Committee on Education and Labor.; United States. Congress. House. Committee on Government Operations.; Labor laws and legislation--United States.; Republican Party (Mich.)
Subject - Visual Materials
Agriculture.; Benton Harbor (Mich.); Clinton (Mich.); Clinton Machine Company.; Dowagiac (Mich.); Erosion.; Ford Motor Company.; Hamilton Farm Bureau Feed Plant (Hamilton, Mich.); Industry.; Industrial buildings.; James Heddon's Sons.; Kalamazoo (Mich.); Laborers.; Law enforcement--United States.; Michigan, Lake.; National Motor Castings Company.; Ohio.; Pickets.; Police--Michigan.; Remington Rand, inc.; Shakespeare Company (Kalamazoo, Mich.); Shoreham (Mich.); South Haven (Mich.); Strikes.; Vandalism.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Combined files 1934-1943, 3.5 linear feet
  These are a miscellanea of files that somehow escaped Hoffman's decision to discard retired materials in 1942. Despite their scattered character, these files are nevertheless substantive in content, relating in great part to Hoffman's criticism of the Wagner Act and the workings of the National Labor Relations Board. These files concern cases of companies experiencing strikes or other labor difficulties. In 1939, for example, Hoffman visited the Appalachian coal fields and kept files for each of the companies he investigated. These Combined Files also document Hoffman's reputation as an anti-New Deal, Anti-Roosevelt, anti-union critic. His activities led to well-publicized confrontations with columnist Walter Winchell for one, and these Hoffman files have much information from, or about, individuals representing both ends of the political spectrum.
  - 1934-1936
    - South Haven Harbor (Box 1)
  - 1937
    - Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen (Box 1)
    - National Labor Relations Board
      - General Cable Corporation (Ed. W. Hamilton) (Box 1)
      - Hosiery mills (Raymond Trautman) (Box 1)
    - South Haven Harbor (Box 1)
    - Three Rivers Fur Tannery (Box 1)
    - Worker Education Program (Box 1)
  - 1938
    - American Vigilant Intelligence Federation (Box 1)
    - Correspondence (miscellaneous) (Box 1)
    - National Labor Relations Board
      - Calcocraft Co. (Ed. W. Hamilton) (Box 1)
      - Consumers Power Company (Box 1)
      - General (Box 1)
      - Hoffman speech (Box 1)
        (distribution of speech as unfair labor practice)
      - Hosiery mills (Raymond Trautman) (Box 1)
      - National Motor Bearing Co. (Box 1)
      - Remington Rand, Inc. (Box 1)
      - Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Box 1)
      - Weirton Steel Company (Box 1)
    - South Haven Harbor (Box 1)
    - Strikes, labor troubles, etc. (Box 1)
    - Wagner Act (efforts to amend) (Box 1)
  - 1939
    - American Vigilant Intelligence Federation (Box 1)
    - Christian Labor Association (Box 1)
    - Chrysler-Dodge strike
      - Correspondence (Box 1)
      - Published material (Box 1)
        (includes Dickinson correspondence)
    - C.I.O. (Box 1)
    - Coal strike investigations
      - Clover Fork Coal Co. (Box 1)
      - Creech Coal Co. (Box 1)
      - Crummies Creek Coal Co. (Box 1)
      - Harlan County miscellanea (Box 1)
      - Harlan Collieries Co. (include photos) (Box 1)
      - Kentucky Cardinal Coal Co. (Box 1)
      - Mahan-Ellison Coal Corp. (Box 1)
      - Southern Mining Co. (Insull Mine) (Box 1)
    - National Labor Relations Board
      - Calcocraft Co.(Edward W. Hamilton) (Box 1)
      - General (complaints, etc.) (Box 1)
      - Investigating Committee (Box 1)
    - Rifle confiscation (Jesse Seeley) (file continues into 1940) (Box 1)
    - Strikes, labor troubles, etc. (Box 1)
    - Wagner Act
      - Correspondence, 3 folders (Box 1)
      - Published material and related used in preparation of Clare E. Hoffman's bill (Box 1)
    - Yankee Springs Recreational Area (Barry County) (Box 1)
  - 1940
    - American Vigilant Intelligence Federation (Box 1)
    - Eastern Press Exchange press releases, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Grand Marais fishermen ("Judith C") (Box 2)
    - Juno, Irene (Harlan, Kentucky) (Box 2)
    - Labor Committee (Box 2)
    - LaFollette Bill (S. 1970) (Box 2)
    - M. Hale & Company (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence (Box 2)
    - National Labor Relations Board
      - Smith Special Committee Investigating the NLRB (Box 2)
    - Strikes, labor trouble, etc.
      - General (Box 2)
      - Akron (Box 2)
      - Detroit (Box 2)
      - Flint (Box 2)
      - Methodist Building (Box 2)
      - National Press Club Cafeteria (Box 2)
      - Toledo (Box 2)
    - Unions
      - General (Box 2)
      - Employment on national defense projects (Box 2)
    - Wagner Act
      - General (Box 2)
      - Individual Complaints (Box 2)
      - CEH amendments (Box 2)
      - Minority Report (Box 2)
      - No Reply (Box 2)
    - Yankee Springs Recreational Area (Barry County) (Box 2)
  - 1941
    - American Vigilant Intelligence Federation (Box 2)
    - Correspondence (Box 2)
    - Eastern Press Exchange (Box 2)
    - Hoffman Talks
      (responses to speeches and requests for copies)
      - Impeach Roosevelt speech and subsequent impeachment speeches (Box 2)
      - M. Lowenstein and Sons (Box 2)
        ("Reds seek control of office workers")
      - Anti-"Union Now" speech (Box 2)
    - Union-related papers and correspondence (Box 2)
  - 1942
    - American Vigilant Intelligence Federation (Box 2)
    - Dilling, Elizabeth (Box 2)
    - Doe, John (correspondent and sender of political news articles) (Box 3)
    - Friends of Democracy (Box 3)
    - Hoffman talks (responses to speeches and requests for copies)
      - "Don't Haul Down the Stars and Stripes" (January 27 and 30), 7 folders (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence (Box 3)
    - Union-related papers and correspondence (Box 3)
    - Winchell, Walter (correspondence and papers about) (Box 3)
  - 1943
    - American Vigilant Intelligence Federation (Box 3)
    - Banta, Edwin (Box 3)
    - Brewster Aeronautical Corp. (Box 3)
    - Commendatory letters from outside district, 3 folders (Box 3)
    - Hamilton Farm Bureau (Box 3)
    - Hoffman Talks (responses to speeches and requests for copies), 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Knowles, Beatrice M. (American Mothers) (Box 3)
    - Murray Packing Company (Box 3)
    - Office of Price Administration, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Port Huron milkdrivers (Box 4)
    - Union-related papers and correspondence (Box 4)
    - Winchell, Walter (Box 4)
- General Files 1944-1962, 21.5 linear feet
  Biennial (except for 1944 through 1946), the General Files series is comprised of correspondence documenting the relationships Hoffman maintained within his district, frequently with small businessmen and with local manufacturers. These files are arranged alphabetically, primarily by name of individual or organization, although there are general category file headings such as: Complaints, Hoffman House Talks, and Newspapers.
  - 1944
    - A (miscellaneous) (Box 4)
    - Adverse
      - In district (Box 4)
      - Out of district (Box 4)
    - American Federation of Labor (communications with) (Box 4)
    - American Vigilant Intelligence Federation (Harry Jung) (Box 4)
    - B (miscellaneous) (Box 4)
    - Banta, Edwin (Box 4)
    - Boyd, L.A. (Michigan Fruit Sponsors) (Box 4)
    - Burnette, William A. (Box 4)
    - C (miscellaneous) (Box 4)
    - Commendatory
      - In district (Box 4)
      - Out of district (Box 4)
      - Weekly letter responses (Box 4)
    - Complaints
      - Communism (Box 4)
      - Farmers (Box 4)
      - Income tax forms (Box 4)
      - Servicemen (Box 4)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
    - Congress of Industrial Organizations (and affiliates) (Box 4)
    - Constitutional Educational League (Joseph P. Kamp) (Box 4)
    - D (miscellaneous) (Box 4)
    - Dilling, Elizabeth (Box 4)
    - E (miscellaneous) (Box 4)
    - F (miscellaneous) (Box 4)
    - G (miscellaneous) (Box 4)
    - H (miscellaneous) (Box 4)
    - Harrah, W. F. (National-Standard Co., Niles, Michigan) (Box 4)
    - Hoffman House Talks (responses to speeches and requests for copies)
      - General (Box 4)
      - "Don't Haul Down the Stars and Stripes" (Box 4)
        (anti-Union Now speech made in 1942)
      - Walter Winchell speeches, 3 folders (Box 5)
    - Hoffman Reprints (distribution of reprints of others) (Box 5)
    - I (miscellaneous) (Box 5)
    - Invitations (Box 5)
    - J (miscellaneous) (Box 5)
    - Jewish (Box 5)
      (CEH filed anti-semitic correspondence here)
    - K (miscellaneous) (Box 5)
    - Knowles, Beatrice M. (national chairman, American Mothers) (Box 5)
    - L (miscellaneous) (Box 5)
    - Law (Box 5)
    - M (miscellaneous) (Box 5)
    - Mc (miscellaneous) (Box 5)
    - Michigan Mushroom Co. (Myron C. Herrick) (Box 5)
    - Montgomery Ward Co. (Box 5)
    - N (miscellaneous) (Box 5)
    - National Labor Relations Board (Box 5)
    - New Deal (Box 5)
      (Correspondence re: CEH criticism of)
    - Newspapers
      - In district (Box 5)
      - Out of district (Box 5)
        (includes columnists and radio commentators)
    - O (miscellaneous) (Box 5)
    - P (miscellaneous) (Box 5)
    - R (miscellaneous) (Box 5)
    - S (miscellaneous) (Box 5)
    - Sayre, Homer D. (National Metal Trades Association) (Box 5)
    - Smith, Gerald L. K. (Box 5)
    - South Haven Fruit Exchange (Cornelius Bus, manager) (Box 5)
    - Speaking Engagements (Box 5)
    - Strikes, labor troubles, etc. (Box 5)
    - Stickler, C.L. (Box 5)
    - Sullivan, George E. (Washington, D.C. attorney) (Box 5)
    - T (miscellaneous) (Box 5)
    - Thomas, W.D. (Box 5)
    - U (miscellaneous) (Box 5)
    - Union Now (organizations and correspondence related to) (Box 5)
    - Unions (Box 5)
    - V (miscellaneous) (Box 5)
    - W (miscellaneous) (Box 5)
    - War Labor Board (National) (Box 5)
  - 1945
    - A (miscellaneous) (Box 5)
    - Adverse, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - American Federation of Labor (communications with) (Box 5)
    - American Vigilant Intelligence Federation (Harry Jung) (Box 5)
    - Ayers, Claude W. (Cassopolis, Michigan, correspondent) (Box 5)
    - B (miscellaneous) (Box 5)
    - Boyd, L.A. (Michigan Fruit Sponsors) (Box 5)
    - Burnette Castings Co.: re: prices on castings, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - C (miscellaneous) (Box 6)
    - Commendatory
      - In district (Box 6)
      - Out of district (Box 6)
      - Weekly news letter responses (Box 6)
    - Communists - Communism (Box 6)
    - Complaints
      - Farmers (Box 6)
      - Meat shortage (Box 6)
      - Servicemen (Box 6)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 6)
    - Congress of Industrial Organizations (and affiliates) (Box 6)
    - Constitutional Educational League (Joseph P. Kamp) (Box 6)
    - D (miscellaneous) (Box 6)
    - Dilling, Elizabeth (Box 6)
    - E (miscellaneous) (Box 6)
    - F (miscellaneous) (Box 6)
    - G (miscellaneous) (Box 6)
    - H (miscellaneous) (Box 6)
    - Harrah, W. F. (National Standards Co., Niles, Michigan) (Box 6)
    - Hoffman House Talks (responses to speeches and requests for copies)
      - General (Box 6)
      - Jefferson Island (Box 6)
      - Kent (Tyler) talk, 2 copies (Box 6)
      - Living Costs (Box 6)
      - Pearson (Drew) column talk (Box 6)
      - Radio talks on labor (Box 6)
    - Invitations (Box 7)
    - J (miscellaneous) (Box 7)
    - Jewish (Box 7)
    - K (miscellaneous) (Box 7)
    - Knowles, Beatrice M. (Box 7)
    - L (miscellaneous) (Box 7)
    - Law (Box 7)
    - M (miscellaneous) (Box 7)
    - Mc (miscellaneous) (Box 7)
    - Montgomery Ward Co. (Box 7)
    - N (miscellaneous) (Box 7)
    - New Deal (Box 7)
    - Newspapers
      - In district (Box 7)
      - Out of district (Box 7)
    - O (miscellaneous) (includes OPA) (Box 7)
    - P (miscellaneous) (Box 7)
    - Political Action Committee of CIO (Box 7)
    - Q (miscellaneous) (Box 7)
    - Questionnaires (Rarely completed, but with occasional information)
    - R (miscellaneous) (Box 7)
    - Remaking America (Box 7)
    - Roosevelt dogs (Box 7)
      (controversy over transport of FOR animals)
    - S (miscellaneous) (Box 7)
    - Signature Missing (Box 7)
    - Small Business (Box 7)
    - Smith, Gerald L.K. (Box 7)
    - South Haven Fruit Exchange (Box 7)
    - Speaking Engagements (Box 7)
    - Strikes, labor troubles, etc. (Box 7)
    - Sullivan, George E. (Box 7)
    - T (miscellaneous) (Box 7)
    - U (miscellaneous) (Box 7)
    - Union Now (Box 7)
    - Unions (general) (Box 7)
    - V (miscellaneous) (Box 7)
    - W (miscellaneous) (Box 7)
    - Wallace, Henry (Box 7)
    - XYZ (miscellaneous) (Box 7)
  - 1946
    - A (miscellaneous) (Box 7)
    - Administration (general criticism of) (Box 7)
    - Adverse
      - In district (Box 7)
      - Out of district (Box 7)
    - American Federation of Labor (communications with) (Box 7)
    - American Vigilant Intelligence Federation (Harry A. Jung) (Box 7)
    - Ayers, Claude W. (Cassopolis, Michigan, correspondent) (Box 7)
    - B (miscellaneous) (Box 7)
    - Benedict, Ben (Box 7)
    - Boyd, L.A. (Michigan Fruit Sponsors) (Box 7)
    - Broker, William (Colon, Michigan, correspondent) (Box 7)
    - Burnette, William A. (Burnette Castings Co.) (Box 7)
    - C (miscellaneous) (Box 7)
    - Camfield, Alfred B. (Box 8)
    - Commendatory
      - In district (Box 8)
      - Out of district (Box 8)
    - Communists - Communism (Box 8)
    - Complaints
      - Servicemen (Box 8)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 8)
    - Conference of American Small Business Organizations (Box 8)
    - Congress of Industrial Organizations (and affiliates) (Box 8)
    - Constitutional Educational League (Joseph P. Kamp) (Box 8)
    - D (miscellaneous) (Box 8)
    - E (miscellaneous) (Box 8)
    - F (miscellaneous) (Box 8)
    - G (miscellaneous) (Box 8)
    - General Motors Strike (Box 8)
    - H (miscellaneous) (Box 8)
    - Hamilton Farm Bureau (includes photos) (Box 8)
    - Harrah, W.F. (National-Standard Co., Niles, Michigan) (Box 8)
    - Hoffman House Talks: responses to speeches and requests for copies
      - General (Box 8)
    - Hoffman Radio Talks
      - CIO-PAC in politics (Box 8)
      - Closed Shop (Box 8)
      - FEPC (Box 8)
      - Minimum Wage (Box 8)
    - Invitations (Box 8)
    - J (miscellaneous) (Box 8)
    - Jones, A. L. (Armstrong Machine Works, Three Rivers, Michigan) (Box 8)
    - K (miscellaneous) (Box 8)
    - Knowles, Beatrice M. (Box 8)
    - L (miscellaneous) (Box 8)
    - Law (Box 8)
    - Lillie, Leo C. (Grand Haven, Michigan, attorney) (Box 8)
    - Luttrell, R.E. (Box 8)
    - M (miscellaneous) (Box 8)
    - Mc (miscellaneous) (Box 8)
    - N (miscellaneous) (Box 8)
    - Newspapers
      - In district (Box 8)
      - Out of district (Box 8)
    - O (miscellaneous) (Box 8)
    - P (miscellaneous) (Box 8)
    - Questionnaires (Rarely completed, but with occasional information) (Box 8)
    - R (miscellaneous) (Box 8)
    - S (miscellaneous) (Box 8)
    - Sayre, Homer D. (National Metal Trades Association) (Box 8)
    - Smith, Gerald L.K. (Box 8)
    - South Haven Fruit Exchange (Cornelius Bus, manager) (Box 8)
    - Speaking Engagements (Box 8)
    - Strikes, labor troubles, etc. (Box 8)
    - Sullivan, George E. (Washington, D.C. attorney) (Box 8)
    - T (miscellaneous) (Box 9)